<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>graphs on LeiMath</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/tags/graphs/</link><description>Recent content in graphs on LeiMath</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://leimath.github.io/tags/graphs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 9</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p9/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p9/</guid><description>This is the final part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Tournaments.
Tournaments So far all the graphs encountered were undirected that is, none of the edges that stood for &amp;ldquo;relationship&amp;rdquo; between two vertex had any direction. If we attach some directional information to an edge, then the graph is called a directed graph. Let the directional information be represented by an arrow which points to a vertex from another vertex, the from side has the arrow and is called an arc in literature.</description><content>&lt;p>This is the final part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Tournaments.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="tournaments">Tournaments&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>So far all the graphs encountered were &lt;code>undirected&lt;/code> that is, none of the edges that stood for &amp;ldquo;relationship&amp;rdquo; between two vertex had any direction. If we attach some directional information to an edge, then the graph is called a &lt;code>directed&lt;/code> graph. Let the directional information be represented by an arrow which points &lt;em>to&lt;/em> a vertex &lt;em>from&lt;/em> another vertex, the &lt;em>from&lt;/em> side has the arrow and is called an &lt;code>arc&lt;/code> in literature. If there is an arc from $v_i$ to $v_j$ then the pair is represented as $(v_i,v_j)$ and the order is fixed. A directed graph is represented as $G = (V,U)$ where the $V$ stands for the usual vertex set and $U$ stands for the arc set composed of directed pairs like $(v_i,v_j)$ etc if an arc exists. The directed graph also follow the &lt;em>simple&lt;/em> nature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The number of arcs which have the starting point from $v_i$ have a name, &lt;code>outdegree&lt;/code> represented by $d^{\star}(v_i)$. Similarly the number of arcs whose arrow points to $v_i$ also have a name, &lt;code>indegree&lt;/code> represented by $d^{\circ}(v)$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We call a directed graph a &lt;code>tournament&lt;/code> if the graph contains $n$ vertices and there is only one arc joining every two vertices. We denote the directed graph by $\overline{K_n}$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a directed graph $D = (V,U)$ let there exist distinct arcs $u_i$. If the starting point of $u_i$ is $v_i$ and endpoint of $u_i$ is $v_{i+1}$ for $i \in \lbrace 1,2,3, \ldots , n \rbrace $ then $n$ is called the length of the directed path from $v_1$ to $v_{n+1}$, and if $v_1 = v_{n+1}$ then this path is called a circuit.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="theorems">Theorems&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 1&lt;/code>: Let $v_i$ be the vertices of a tournament $\overline{K_n}$ for $i \in \lbrace 1,2,3, \ldots \rbrace$ then, $$\sum\limits_{k=1}^n d^{\star}(v_k) = \sum\limits_{k=1}^n d^{\circ}(v_k) = \frac{1}{2} n (n-1)$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 2&lt;/code>: There exists a vertex in a tournament so that there is a path from it to any other vertices. The maximum length of the paths is 2.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 3&lt;/code>: If the vertex of $\overline{K_n}$ with maximum outdegree is unique, then this outdegree is $n-1$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 4&lt;/code>: Tournament $\overline{K_n}$ contains a Hamiltonian path whose length is $n-1$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 5&lt;/code>: The tournament $\overline{K_n}$ for $n \geqslant 3$ contains a circuit which is a triangle, if and only if there are two vertices $v,v^{\prime}$ which satisfy $$d^{\star}(v) = d^{\circ}(v^{\prime})$$&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>1.&lt;/code> Prove that if a tournament $\overline{K_n}$ contains a circuit, then $\overline{K_n} contains a triangular circuit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>2.&lt;/code> There are $100$ species of insects. Among every two of them
there is one species who can eliminate another species. (But A
eliminates B, B eliminates C, which does not mean that A eliminates
C . ) Prove that the $100$ species of insects can be arranged in an order so
that any species can perish another species next to it.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 7</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p7/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p7/</guid><description>This is the seventh part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Planar Graphs.
The book followed throughout is: Graph Theory with Applications by Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.
Planar Graphs A graph is called Planar if it can be drawn in the plane so that its edges intersect only at their ends.
The vertices and edges of the graph partition (no overlap) the plane into several regions, each such region is called a face, denoted by $F_i$ for some $i \in \mathbb{N}$.</description><content>&lt;p>This is the seventh part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Planar Graphs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book followed throughout is: &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em>. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="planar-graphs">Planar Graphs&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>A graph is called &lt;code>Planar&lt;/code> if it can be drawn in the plane so that its edges intersect only at their ends.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The vertices and edges of the graph partition (no overlap) the plane into several regions, each such region is called a &lt;code>face&lt;/code>, denoted by $F_i$ for some $i \in \mathbb{N}$. The only unbound face which exists is the &lt;code>outer&lt;/code> face, the others are termed as &lt;code>inner&lt;/code> faces.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Two graphs $G_1,G_2$ are called &lt;code>homeomorphic&lt;/code> if $G_1$ can be obtained by inserting some new &lt;strong>vertices&lt;/strong> on $G_2$&amp;rsquo;s edge. By this definition, inserting or deleting a number of 2-degree vertices does not change planarity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note that $K_5$ and $K_{3,3}$ are not planar (Can be proven by Theorem 1/2).&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="theorems">Theorems&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 1[Euler's Formula]&lt;/code>: For a connected planar graph $G$ with $v$ vertice, $e$ edges and $f$ faces, then $$v - e + f = 2.$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 2&lt;/code>: For a connected simple planar graph $G$ with $v ~ (v \geqslant 3)$ vertices and $e$ edges, $$e \leqslant 3v - 6$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is an extension from Euler&amp;rsquo;s Formula, obtained for maximizing edges in a simple planar graph. Theorem 2 also holds for disconnected simple planar graphs. It can also be used to determine if a graph is planar or not.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 3[Kuratowski]&lt;/code>: A graph is planar if and only if it contains no subgraph homeomorphic to $K_5$ and $K_3,3$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A neat proof can be found in the text mentioned above.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 4[Kozyrev-Grinberg]&lt;/code>: If a planar graph has a Hamiltonian cycle $c$, let $f_{i}^{\prime}$ be the number of $i$-polygons inside $c$, and $f_{i}^{\prime \prime}$ be the number of $i$-polygons outside $c$, then&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>$1 \cdot f_{3}^{\prime}+2 \cdot f_{4}^{\prime}+3 \cdot f_{5}^{\prime}+\cdots=n-2$;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$1 \cdot f_{3}^{\prime \prime}+2 \cdot f_{4}^{\prime \prime}+3 \cdot f_{5}^{\prime \prime}+\cdots=n-2$;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$1 \cdot\left(f_{3}^{\prime}-f_{3}^{\prime \prime}\right)+2 \cdot\left(f_{4}^{\prime}-f_{4}^{\prime \prime}\right)+3 \cdot\left(f_{5}^{\prime}-f_{5}^{\prime \prime}\right)+\cdots=0$, where $n$ is the number of the vertices of $G$, and also the length of $c$.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>1.&lt;/code> Prove that the $K_5$ and $K_{3,3}$ are not planar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>2.&lt;/code> In a bus network there are $n$ stations. Each station is connected to at least 6 roads. Prove that there must be two roads intersecting on the plane.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>3.&lt;/code> Let $S=\lbrace x_{1}, x_{2}, \ldots, x_{n}\rbrace ~~ (n \geqslant 3)$ be the set of vertices on the plane. The distance between two arbitrary vertices is no less than 1. Prove that there are at most $3 n-6$ pairs of vertices whose distances are 1 .&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 8</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p8/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p8/</guid><description>This is the eight part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at some theorems mostly related to Ramsey Numbers.
The book followed for the other notes is : Graph Theory with Applications by Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.
For this post, the readers are also encouraged to seek the proofs in other books such as the legendary Adrian Bondy &amp;amp; U.</description><content>&lt;p>This is the eight part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at some theorems mostly related to Ramsey Numbers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book followed for the other notes is : &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em>. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this post, the readers are also encouraged to seek the proofs in other books such as the legendary &lt;em>Adrian Bondy &amp;amp; U.S.R Murty - Graph Theory&lt;/em> from &lt;em>Springer - Verlag&lt;/em> or &lt;em>Graph Theory: A Problem Oriented Approach by Daniel Marcus&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="ramsey-number">Ramsey Number&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Consider $k$ colors, $c_1, c_2, c_3, \ldots, c_k$ to color the complete graph $K_n$. We call $K_n$ as the &lt;code>k-color complete graph&lt;/code> if &lt;strong>every&lt;/strong> edge is colored in one color. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t take much convincing to claim that if $n$ is large enough, $k$-color complete graph $K_n$ must contain a monochromatic triangle. Call the least of such $n$ by $r_k$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$\displaystyle r_k$ is nothing but the &lt;code>Ramsey Number&lt;/code> named after British mathematician Ramsey who proved its existence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Suppose every edge of the complete graph $K_{n}$ is colored in red or blue, which means that $K_{n}$ is a two-color (red, blue) complete graph $K_{n}$. For two constant natural numbers $p, q$, when $n$ is large enough, the two-color (red, blue) complete graph $K_{n}$ must contain a red $K_{p}$ or a blue $K_{q}$. We denote the least $n$ satisfying the above proposition by $r(p, q)$. We also call $r(p, q)$ the Ramsey number.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$r(p,q)$ is hence the minimum $n$ so that any $n$-subgraph $G$ of the complete graph $K_n$ contains a complete subgraph $K_p$ or its complementary graph $\bar{G}$ contains a complete subgraph $K_q$.
Also that, $r(1,q) = r(p,1) = 1$.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="theorems">Theorems&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>All of the proofs are omitted as some are way too long or quite difficult for the needs of these notes&lt;/code>, particularly that they hold no purpose here (or for a Scholarship exam for which these notes are for!) and might as well be referred directly from any standard Graph Theory book - like the ones mentioned below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 1&lt;/code>: If a complete graph $K_n$ in two colors contains a monochromatic triangle, then the minimum $n$ is equal to 6.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For Theorem 1, $r(3,3) = r_2 = 6$.
See &lt;a href="https://math.mit.edu/~apost/courses/18.204_2018/ramsey-numbers.pdf">here, page 2&lt;/a> for a proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 2&lt;/code>: [I] For every positive integer $k$, the Ramsey Number $r_k$ exists. When $k \geqslant 2$, $$r_k \leqslant k(r_{k-1}-1 ) + 2$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[II] For any $k \in \mathbb{N}$, $$r_k \leqslant 1 + 1 + k + k(k-1) + \ldots + \frac{k!}{2!} + \frac{k!}{1!} + k!$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note that Theorem 2 [II] is also written (with the help of series expansion of $e$) as $r_k \leqslant \lfloor k!~e~ \rfloor + 1$ where $\lfloor . \rfloor$ is the greatest integer function.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some hints for the proof can be found &lt;a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1055435/modification-of-the-ramsey-number?noredirect=1">here&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note that $r(2,q) = q$ and $r(p,2) = p$. Also, $r(p,q) = r(q,p)$ See &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em> Page 103, Section 7.2 for the discussion/proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 4&lt;/code> [Ramsey&amp;rsquo;s Theorem] For any two positive integers $n$ and $m$, the number $r(p, q)$ exists and satisfies the inequality $R(p, q) \leq r(p-1, q)+r(p, q-1) .$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a proof see, &lt;em>Adrian Bondy &amp;amp; Murty - Graph Theory (GTM) by Springer - Verlag&lt;/em> Page 309 m, &lt;strong>Theorem 12.5&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 4&lt;/code>: When $p \geqslant 2$ and $q \geqslant 2$ then $$r(p,q) \leqslant \binom{p+q-2}{p-1}$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Proof can be found in &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em> Page 106, Theorem 7.5&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>A lot of questions on Ramsey Numbers can be found &lt;a href="https://artofproblemsolving.com/community/q2_%22ramsey%20number%22">here&lt;/a> and also similarly searching &amp;ldquo;Ramsey&amp;rdquo; in the search field of artofproblemsolving forums. We direct the reader to try them to truly cover the varieties of such questions.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 6</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p6/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p6/</guid><description>This is the sixth part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Hamiltonian Graphs. We omit a tactics section since the questions related to Hamiltonian Graphs are diverse each requiring some approach unique in its own way, please see the #Questions section for further references.
The book followed throughout is: Graph Theory with Applications by Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.</description><content>&lt;p>This is the sixth part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Hamiltonian Graphs. We omit a tactics section since the questions related to Hamiltonian Graphs are diverse each requiring some approach unique in its own way, please see the &lt;strong>#Questions&lt;/strong> section for further references.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book followed throughout is: &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em>. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="hamiltonian-graph">Hamiltonian Graph&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>If a chain exists such that it passes through &lt;strong>every&lt;/strong> vertex only once, then the chain is called a &lt;code>Hamiltonian Chain&lt;/code>, respectively the definition also follows similarly for &lt;code>Hamiltonian Cycles&lt;/code>. Put differently, a Hamiltonian chain is where it visits every vertex
exactly once but need not cover every edge. If a graph contains a Hamiltonian &lt;strong>&lt;em>cycle&lt;/em>&lt;/strong> then the graph is called a &lt;code>Hamiltonian Graph&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note that no nontrivial necessary and sufficient condition for a graph to be Hamiltonian is known, it is one of the main unsolved problem of graph theory. However, there are some negative tests, which can show that a given
graph contains no Hamilton path or cycle, and some positive tests, which can show that
a given graph contains a Hamilton path or cycle without actually constructing one. These
tests do not apply to every graph.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Refer to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CEOGcSCTar8">this&lt;/a> to get a idea on the differences in the Eulerian Graph and Hamiltonian Graphs. Loosely, Eulerian graphs only bother with edges whereas a Hamiltonian graph has to deal with the vertices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="theorems">Theorems&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 1&lt;/code>: In a bigraph $G$ if $|V_1| \neq |V_2|$, $G$ must contain no Hamiltonian cycle. If the difference between $|V_1|$ and $|V_2|$ is more than $1$, $G$ must contain no Hamiltonian chain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 2&lt;/code>: Let $G$ be a simple graph with $n \geqslant 3$ vertices. For every pair of vertices $v,v&amp;rsquo;$ if $$d(v) + d(v&amp;rsquo;) \geqslant n - 1$$ then $G$ contains a Hamiltonian chain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note that the Theorem 2 condition is indeed gives a way for existence of a Hamiltonian chain but it is not necessary. There exists examples (e.g, a regular hexagon) where the condition fails yet the graph is a Hamiltonian chain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 3[Ore]&lt;/code>: Let $G$ be a simple graph with $n$ vertices. For every two nonadjacent vertices $v,v&amp;rsquo;$ if $$d(v) + d(v&amp;rsquo;) \geqslant n$$ then $G$ is a Hamiltonian cycle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 4[Dirac]&lt;/code>: Let $G$ be a simple graph with $n$ vertices. If the degree of every vertex $v$ is no less than $\frac{n}{2}$, then $G$ must contain a Hamiltonian cycle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 5[Pósa]&lt;/code> Let $G$ be a graph with $n$ vertices, where $n \geq 3$, and suppose that the degrees in $G$ satisfy $$d_{1}&amp;gt;1 ~ ,~ d_{2}&amp;gt;2~,~ \ldots ~, ~ d_{i}&amp;gt;i$$ where $d_1,d_2, \ldots, d_i$ represents the degrees of each vertex for all values of $i &amp;lt; \frac{n}{2}$.
Then $G$ contains a Hamilton cycle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is the so called &lt;code>Pósa's theorem&lt;/code>, and in a way &amp;ndash; the combined power form of Theorem 3 and 4.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 6&lt;/code>: If $G$ contains a Hamiltonian graph, remove several vertices $v_1, v_2, v_3, \ldots v_k$ and their adjacent edges from $G$ to get new graph $G^\prime$, then the number of connected components in $G^\prime$ is no more than $k$.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>A lot of different variants of questions are possible and simply listing down tactics wouldn&amp;rsquo;t cover the strategies usually required, hence we recommend the reader to do questions from any standard book (either from the one mentioned at the begining of this post, or &lt;em>Graph Theory: A Problem Oriented Approach by Daniel Marcus, Chapter G&lt;/em>) along with the questions presented below.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>1.&lt;/code> Arrange 7 examinations in 7 days so that the two courses which are taught by one teacher cannot be arranged in two consecutive days. If every teacher can teach at most 4 courses which have examination. Prove that it is possible to arrange the examinations in the above way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>2.&lt;/code> A factory produces two-color paper using 6 distinct colored yarns. Among six kinds of yarns, every color must be matched in groups with three other colors. Prove that it is possible to choose three kinds of two-color paper so that all 6 colors are present.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>3.&lt;/code> If $A_{0} A_{1} A_{2} \ldots A_{2 n-1}$ is a regular polygon of $2 n$ sides. Join all its diagonals to get a graph $G$. Prove that every Hamiltonian cycle of $G$ must contain two edges which are parallel in the graph.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>4.&lt;/code> An executive has $2 n$ friends, among whom there are several friends hate each other. But the number of persons every friend hates is no more than $n-1$. Can they sit in a round table so that no two adjacent friend hate each other?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>5.&lt;/code> Around a table there sit at least five persons and it is possible to rearrange their seats so that beside everyone there are two new neighbours.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 5</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p5/</guid><description>This is the fifth part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Euler&amp;rsquo;s Problem and its resolution in this post.
The book followed throughout is: Graph Theory with Applications by Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.
Regarding the Königsberg Problem The entirety of the Königsberg problem solved by Euler is covered at various places; Please refer to here - for a audiovisual treatment or here - for a full report on it.</description><content>&lt;p>This is the fifth part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Euler&amp;rsquo;s Problem and its resolution in this post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book followed throughout is: &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em>. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="regarding-the-königsberg-problem">Regarding the Königsberg Problem&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The entirety of the Königsberg problem solved by Euler is covered at various places; Please refer to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nZwSo4vfw6c">here - for a audiovisual treatment&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://www.maa.org/press/periodicals/convergence/leonard-eulers-solution-to-the-konigsberg-bridge-problem">here - for a full report on it.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The key question that was put forward against Euler was: Can a traveler go through every bridge once and only once ?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>His solution led to many theorems that came forward and is presented below.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="eulerian-graphs">Eulerian Graphs&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Note that in various instances a &lt;em>chain&lt;/em> is also referred to as a &lt;code>walk&lt;/code>.
A &lt;code>tour&lt;/code> of a graph $G$ is a closed (starts and ends in same vertex) walk that traverses each edge of $G$ &lt;strong>at least&lt;/strong> once.
If a cycle in a graph traverses every edge of the graph &lt;strong>exactly&lt;/strong> once then the cycle is termed as &lt;code>Euler Tour&lt;/code> (old books also call it &lt;code>Euler Trail&lt;/code> as well).
A graph where Euler tour is admitted is called a &lt;code>Eulerian Graph&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A &lt;code>path&lt;/code> is any walk (or, chain) with distinct vertices.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="theorems">Theorems&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 1&lt;/code>: A finite graph $G$ is a chain or a cycle if and only if $G$ is connected and the number of vertices with odd degree in $G$ is equal to $2$ or $0$. When and only when the number of vertices with odd degrees in $G$ is equal to $0$, the connected graph $G$ is a cycle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 2&lt;/code>: If $G$ is a connected graph and has $2k$ odd vertices, then graph $G$ can be drawn by lifting one&amp;rsquo;s pen $k$ times and at least $k$ times.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 3&lt;/code>: A nonempty connected graph is Eulerian if and only if it has
no vertices of odd degree.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 4&lt;/code>: A connected graph has an Euler trail if and only if it has at
most two vertices of odd-degree&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: Some theorems are quite tricky, especially Theorem 1, and non-intuitive. Please refer to the book mentioned above for proofs else, skip them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 5[&amp;quot;Euler Path Theorem&amp;quot;]&lt;/code>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>A graph contains a closed Euler path if and only if&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Every vertex has even degree, and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>All edges are in the same component.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>A graph contains an open Euler path if and only if
(a) Exactly two vertices have odd degree, and
(b) All edges are in the same component.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Note: An Euler path is called &lt;code>closed&lt;/code> if it starts and ends at the same
vertex; otherwise it’s called &lt;code>open&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="tactics">Tactics&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Along with previously discussed tactics, some extra ones are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Coloring&lt;/code>: We try to divide the graph into subgraphs and see if keep some color invariant results in some concrete evaluation of data given in the question paired with the theorems presented above.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Principle of Least Action&lt;/code>: We try to generate a tour which requires the least &lt;em>weightage&lt;/em> (weightage can mean the degree value, moves set or any other restriction) and then try to see at cases which either maximize or minimize some condition respectively.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>1.&lt;/code> Arrange $n$ vertices $v_{1}, v_{2}, \ldots, v_{n}$ in order on a line. Each vertex is colored in red or blue. If the ends of a segment $v_{i} v_{i+1}$ are colored differently, we call it a standard segment. Suppose the colors of $v_{1}$ and $v_{n}$ are different. Prove that the number of the standard segments is odd.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>2.&lt;/code> [CMC 5th] A graph which consists of a convex $n$-polygon and $n-3$ disjoint diagonal lines in the polygon is called a subdivision graph.
Prove that there exists a &lt;code>subdivision graph&lt;/code> which is a cycle drawn without lifting one&amp;rsquo;s pen (i. e. start from a vertex, go through each segment only once and return the starting point) if and only if $3 \mid n$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>3.&lt;/code> On an $8 \times 8$ chessboard with 64 black and white squares we move a knight. In whatever direction the knight moves, is it possible to make the knight move to all the squares and each square only once? (A knight moves from a corner square of a rectangle with $2 \times 3$ black and white squares to another corner square diagonal to the starting position.)&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 4</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p4/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p4/</guid><description>This is the fourth part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Trees.
The book followed throughout is: Graph Theory with Applications by Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.
Trees Before introducing trees, here are some essential terminologies:
Let $G$ be a graph and its edges are $e_1,e_2,e_3,e_4,\ldots,e_m$
If edge $e_i = (v_{i-1},v_i)$ for $i = 1,2,3, \ldots, m$ exists and $v_{i-1}$ is adjacent to $v_i$ then we call the sequence a chain from $v_0$ and $v_m$.</description><content>&lt;p>This is the fourth part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Trees.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book followed throughout is: &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em>. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="trees">Trees&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Before introducing trees, here are some essential terminologies:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let $G$ be a graph and its edges are $e_1,e_2,e_3,e_4,\ldots,e_m$&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>If edge $e_i = (v_{i-1},v_i)$ for $i = 1,2,3, \ldots, m$ exists and $v_{i-1}$ is adjacent to $v_i$ then we call the sequence a &lt;code>chain&lt;/code> from $v_0$ and $v_m$. It is denoted as $v_0v_1\ldots v_m$.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$m$ is called the &lt;code>length&lt;/code> of the chain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If $v_0$ and $v_m$ are the same, then the chain is called a &lt;code>cycle&lt;/code>. Note that the proper definition for a cycle requires all $v_i$ , $i \in \lbrace 2,m-1 \rbrace$ to be distinct and $v_0 = v_m$ however we do not use the distinctness part for use in these notes for simplicity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a graph is not cyclic then it is called acyclic.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a chain exists between &lt;strong>ANY&lt;/strong> two vertices, then the graph is called connected, else the graph is disconnected.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A connected graph which contains no cycle (i.e, acyclic) is called a &lt;code>tree&lt;/code>. It is denoted by $T$. By definition, tree is a simple graph. A tree can be used to construct a graph with more than $n-1$ edges, hence such a tree is called &lt;code>generating tree&lt;/code> of the graph.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A graph without circles must be composed of one or more trees whose vertices are disjoint, such a graph is called a &lt;code>forest&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The vertex of a tree which has degree 1 is called a &lt;code>leaf&lt;/code> or a &lt;code>pendant vertex&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="theorems">Theorems&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 1&lt;/code>: If a tree has no less than two vertices, then it has at least two leaves (pendant vertices).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Proof 1&lt;/em> : Suppose we start from some vertex $u$, along the edges of $T$, every edge can only be passed by once. Since a tree has no cycle, it cannot return to the vertices which have been passed. It means that each vertex can be passed at most once. If the vertex we pass is not a pendant vertex, because its degree is more than 1 , we can continue. But the number of vertices of $T$ is finite, so it is impossible to continue forever. If we cannot continue further at $v$, then $v$ is a pendant vertex.
We start from a pendant vertex $v$ and we can end up at another pendant vertex $v^{\prime}$. So tree $T$ has at least two pendant vertices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Proof 2&lt;/em> : Assume that $\mu=u v_{1} v_{2} \cdots v_{k} v$ is the longest chain of $T$, we can show that $d(u)=d(v)=1$, i.e. $u, v$ are pendant vertices.
In fact, if $d(u) \geqslant 2$, then there exists vertex $w\left(w \neq v_{1}\right)$ adjacent to $u$. If $w$ is one of $v_{2}, \ldots, v_{k}, v$, then a cycle occurs. It contradicts the definition of tree. If $w$ is different from $v_{2}, \ldots, v_{k}$, $v$, then $w u v_{1} \cdots v_{k} v$ is a chain longer than $\mu$, a contradiction. So $d(u)=1$. Similarly, $d(v)=1$. Hence tree $T$ has at least two pendant vertices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 2[Pósa]&lt;/code> Let $V$ be the set of all the vertices of $G, E$ the set of all the edges of $G$. If $|E| \geqslant|V|+4$, then there must be two cycles which have no common edges.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 3&lt;/code>: Let $n$ be the number of vertices of $T$, then the number of edges of $T$ is $n - 1$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 4&lt;/code>: Let $T$ be a graph with $n$ vertices and $e$ edges. Then the following three propositions are equivalent:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>$T$ is a tree&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$T$ has no cycle, and edges of $T$ equal $n-1$&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$T$ is connected, and edges of $T$ equal $n-1$&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 5&lt;/code>: If $T$ is a tree then $T$ is connected, but after deleting any edge of $T$, the obtained graph $G$ is disconnected.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Corollary&lt;/code>: If $T$ is a tree and $T$ then after adding an edge the obtained graph contains only one unique cycle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Optimization of Tree&lt;/code>: Tree is a graph with the least number of edges. Tree is also a graph without a cycle which the has the most possible number of edges.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 6&lt;/code>: In any graph $G$, let $e$ denote the number of edges and $n$ be the number of vertices. If $e &amp;lt; n - 1$ then $G$ is disconnected. If $e &amp;gt; n -1$ then $G$ must have a cycle&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 7&lt;/code>: If there is only one chain between any two vertices of $T$ then $T$ must be a tree.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 8&lt;/code>: A graph is bipartite if and only if it contains no odd cycle&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="tactics">Tactics&lt;/h1>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Proof by construction&lt;/code>: Theorem 1 Proof 1 is an example. It can be employed when the given question is intuitvely obvious enough.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Longest Chain Method&lt;/code>: Theorem 2 Proof 2 is an example. It relies on the principles of Neighbourhood Dragging (more accurately, the reverse principle of neighbourhood dragging) as discussed in Part 1 of the notes. We pick an element and argue if the neighbours belong in the chain or not to reach some sort of contradiction.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>1.&lt;/code> Prove Theorem 2 above.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>2.&lt;/code> [USAMO 1986] In a lecture, there are five mathematicians. Each of them took a nap twice and every two of them took naps at the same time. Prove that there must be three persons who took naps at the same time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>3.&lt;/code> Given a number table with $n$ rows and $n$ columns, every two rows are different. Prove that there must exist a column, after deleting it, every two rows are still different.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>4.&lt;/code> [CMC 1987] $n(n&amp;gt;3)$ table tennis players play several single games. The opponents of any two players are different. Prove that we can remove one player so that the opponents of any two players in the remaining players are still different.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>5.&lt;/code> If a graph $G$ has $n$ vertices and $n-1$ edges, then $G$ is a tree. Prove or disprove.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 3</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p3/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p3/</guid><description>This is the third part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at $k$-partite graphs and Turán&amp;rsquo;s Theorem. We omit the Tactics section since most problems can be handled by tactics mentioned earlier combined with the powerful results mentioned below. However, it might be worthwhile to see the connection of Inequalities (like - AM-GM, Cauchy-Schwartz etc) to problems related with finding bounds of edges.
The book followed throughout is: Graph Theory with Applications by Bondy J.</description><content>&lt;p>This is the third part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at $k$-partite graphs and Turán&amp;rsquo;s Theorem. We omit the Tactics section since most problems can be handled by tactics mentioned earlier combined with the powerful results mentioned below. However, it might be worthwhile to see the connection of Inequalities (like - AM-GM, Cauchy-Schwartz etc) to problems related with finding bounds of edges.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book followed throughout is: &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em>. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="k-partite-graphs">$k$-partite Graphs&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Let $G$ be a graph with with the vertex set $V$ then if&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>The vertex set can be decomposed into a union of $k$ subsets such that any two subsets are disjoint i.e $$V = \bigcup\limits_{i = 1}^k V_i \qquad V_i \cap V_j = \phi$$ for some $i \neq j$&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is no edge whose two vertices are in the same subset&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>then if these two conditions are met, we call a graph &lt;code>k-partite&lt;/code>. A 2-partite graph is called a &lt;code>bigraph&lt;/code> (which are the same as previously defined term, &lt;em>bipartite graph&lt;/em>). A $k$-partite graph is denoted by $G = (V_1,V_2,\dots,V_k;E)$ or $G = (V_1^k;E)$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is not difficult to convince oneself that any graph with $n$ vertices is $n$-partite graph.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Suppose that $G^\prime$ is a &lt;em>simple&lt;/em> $k$-partite graph as in $G^\prime = (V_1^k;E)$ with $| V_i| = m_i$, $i \in \lbrace 1,2,3, \ldots \rbrace$. The graph is said to be &lt;code>complete k-partite&lt;/code> if &lt;strong>any&lt;/strong> two vertices belonging in two different subsets of the vertex set $V^\prime$ are adjacent, i.e, $u \in V_i , v \in V_j , i \neq j$ and $u$ is adjacent to $v$. We denote the graph $G^\prime$ as $K_{m_1, m_2, \dots , m_k}$ and more frequent notation is $T_{k}(n)$ where $n$ stands for the total number of vertices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A complete bigraph is shown below, denoted as $K_{2,3}$ or $T_3 (5)$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://leimath.github.io/assets/images/complete-bigraph.png" alt="A complete bigraph">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Complete bigraphs do not contain triangles made with the vertices of the graph itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A complete graph and a complete $k$-partite graph are $k$-regular for some $k$.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="theorems">Theorems&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 1&lt;/code>: If a graph $G$ with $n$ vertices contains no triangle, the largest number of edges of $G$ is $\left[\frac{n^2}{4}\right]$ where $\left [ .\right]$ represents the greatest integer function.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hint: Prove by Induction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 2 [Turán]&lt;/code>: Suppose $G$ contains no $K_{k+1}$, then $e(G) \leqslant e(T_{k}(n))$. The equality holds if and only if $G \cong T_{k}(n)$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Key: The $\cong$ represents &amp;lsquo;isomorphic&amp;rsquo;. The $e(.)$ stands for the number of edges. $G$ is any simple graph. $T_{k}(n)$ represents a complete $k$-partite graph with $n$ vertices. $K_{k+1}$ is the complete graph with $k+1$ vertices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The proof can be found in the book &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em> as was mentioned in Part 1 of these notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note 1: This theorem&amp;rsquo;s proof is not necessary for olympiads/scholarship exams. Theorem 1 is rather common and is sometimes referred to Turán&amp;rsquo;s theorem as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note 2: $e(T_k(n)) = \binom{n - k}{2} + (m-1)\binom{k+1}{2}$ where $k = \lfloor \frac{n}{m} \rfloor$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dotsb$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Theorem 3&lt;/code>: [&amp;ldquo;Marriage Lemma&amp;rdquo; or Hall&amp;rsquo;s Matching Theorem] Let $G$ be a bipartite graph with parts $A$ and $B$. Suppose that $B$ has at least as many vertices as $A$. Then $G$ has a matching using all the vertices of $A$ if and only if for any subset $S$ of $k$ vertices of $A$, there are at least $k$ vertices in $B$ adjacent to some vertex of $A$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In particular, if every vertex of $A$ has the same degree $a$ and every vertex of $B$ has the same degree $b$, then $G$ has a matching using every vertex of $A$.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>1.&lt;/code> Prove that if there are $2n+1$ vertices and $n^2 + n + 1$ edges in a simple graph $G$, then $G$ must contain a triangle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>2.&lt;/code> $G$ is a graph with $n$ vertices and $n+1$ edges. Prove that there exists at least one vertex whose degree is no less than 3.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>3.&lt;/code> In a circular city whose radius is 6 kilometers, there are 18 police cars making the rounds. They use wireless equipments to communicate with each other. If the wireless is effective within 9 kilometers. Prove that at any time, there must exist two cars, each of them can communicate with five other cars.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 2</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p2/</guid><description>This is the second part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Degree of a Vertex and the so-called Hand-Shaking Lemma in this post.
The book followed throughout is: Graph Theory with Applications by Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.
Degree of a Vertex The degree of a vertex $v$ in a graph $G$, denoted by $d_G(v)$ (or simply, $d(v)$ if the context of graph is clear), is the number of edges incident to $v$ of $G$.</description><content>&lt;p>This is the second part of the graph theory notes. We take a look at Degree of a Vertex and the so-called Hand-Shaking Lemma in this post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book followed throughout is: &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em>. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="degree-of-a-vertex">Degree of a Vertex&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The &lt;code>degree&lt;/code> of a vertex $v$ in a graph $G$, denoted by $d_G(v)$ (or simply, $d(v)$ if the context of graph is clear), is the number of edges incident to $v$ of $G$. Each loop is counted as two edges. $\delta(G)$ and $\Delta(G)$ are used to represent the minimum and maximum degrees of the vertices of $G$ respectively. A vertex is odd if the degree is odd, else it is even.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let $G(V,E)$ be a graph where $V,E$ are the vertex and edge set respectively. If it happens that for ALL vertex $v$, $d(v) = k$ for some $k$, then the graph $G$ is called &lt;code>k-regular&lt;/code>. The complete graph on $n$ vertices is $(n-1)$ regular.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="theorems">Theorems&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Theorem[I]: For any graph $G$ with $n$ vertices, the sum of degrees of all the vertices is twice as large as the number of edges. In symbols, if the $n$ vertices are $V = \lbrace v_1, v_2, \dots, v_n \rbrace$ then $$\sum\limits_{k = 1}^n d(v_k) = 2 |E|$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is popularly known as the &lt;code>Hand-Shaking Lemma&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Theorem[II]: In any &lt;em>finite&lt;/em> graph $G$, the number of vertices with odd degree is even.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Theorem[III]: A vertex is at most adjacent to other $n-1$ vertices in a simple graph on $n$ vertices i.e $$d(v) \leqslant n-1$$ for all $v \in V.$&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Let there be $n$ vertices of type $x$ all contained in the set $X$ i.e, $X = \lbrace x_1, x_2, \dots, x_n \rbrace$ and $m$ vertices of type $y$ in $Y$ as $Y = \lbrace y_1, y_2, \dots, y_m\rbrace$ then $X \cap Y = \phi$ and if we connect $x_i$ with $y_i$ if a relationship exists then an edge $(x_i, y_i)$ is formed. This graph $G$ is called a &lt;code>bipartite&lt;/code> graph, or &lt;code>even&lt;/code> graph and is denoted by $G = (X,Y; E)$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If $G$ is a simple graph on $n$ vertices, then if we generate a graph by deleting all the edges belonging to $G$ from the complete graph $K_n$, this is called the &lt;code>complementary&lt;/code> graph of G, denoted by $\bar{G}$.
The complement of the graph with $n$ vertices and no edges is the complete graph on $n$ vertices, and is denoted $K_{n}$.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="tactics">Tactics&lt;/h1>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Looking for some contradiction with the use of Hand-Shaking Lemma.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Selectively looking for what the degree of a vertex value can be.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Looking at the subgraph by deleting some edges, vertices and then reaching some contradiction.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Getting bounds on the degree of all vertex values.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Viewing $d(v)$ as some algebraic object to use inequalities in it.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>1.&lt;/code> Show that at any party, there are always at least two people with exactly the
same number of friends at the party.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>2.&lt;/code> A cube with edge of length $n$ is cut into $n^3$ unit cubes by planes parallel to its sides. How many pairs of unit cubes whose common vertices are no more than $2$ are there?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>3.&lt;/code> There are $n$ points on the plane. Prove that the number of pairs of points whose distance is $1$ would not exceed $$\frac{n}{4} + \frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}n^{\frac{3}{2}}$$&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>My Graph Theory Notes - Part 1</title><link>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://leimath.github.io/posts/gt-notes-p1/</guid><description>This is a series of my notes on graph theory and usage in Scholarship Problems. We look at what a graph is today and present some terminologies. We also present some basic tactics to solve elementary problems.
Following the tradition of this blog, we do not present any illustrations on using the tactics as it limits the readers to thinking about the problems only through a specific approach whereas in an exam environment multiple approaches and various combination of techniques is necessary.</description><content>&lt;p>This is a series of my notes on graph theory and usage in Scholarship Problems. We look at what a graph is today and present some terminologies. We also present some basic tactics to solve elementary problems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Following the tradition of this blog, we do not present any illustrations on using the tactics as it limits the readers to thinking about the problems only through a specific approach whereas in an exam environment multiple approaches and various combination of techniques is necessary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book followed throughout is: &lt;em>Graph Theory with Applications&lt;/em> by &lt;em>Bondy J.A., Murty U.S.R.&lt;/em>. Please refer to the book for examples as well as visual graph drawings.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="graphs">Graphs&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>A graph is a set of points with certain vertices joined by some edge. The graph represents a binary relationship.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When to look through a Graph Theoritic perspective ? Whenever there is a clear-cut distinction provided in the question as some &amp;ldquo;objects&amp;rdquo; and some &amp;ldquo;relationship&amp;rdquo; between the objects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To represent such objects, we use a point and call it &amp;ldquo;vertex&amp;rdquo; and to signify the relationship between two vertex, we draw a line between them and call it an &amp;ldquo;edge&amp;rdquo;. Whatever figure this generates, we call it a graph.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We present the proper definition just for the sake of completeness.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Graph[Definition]: A graph is a triplet $(V,E,\varphi)$ where $V$ and $E$ are two disjoint sets, $V$ is non-empty and $\varphi$ is a mapping from $V \times V \to E.$ The set $V$ is the vertex set, $E$ is called the edge set an $\varphi$ is the incidence function.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Rules for Graphs:&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>$\qquad$ [I] It is allowed that vertices and edges may not be in the same plane&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$\qquad$ [II] It is NOT allowed for an edge to pass through a third vertex&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$\qquad$ [III] It is NOT allowed for an edge to intersect itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>For two graphs $G_1, G_2$ if there exists a bijection between the vertices of $G_1$ to $G_2$ such that the number of edges joining two points in $G_1$ equals the number the edges joining two in $G_2$, then we call such two graphs $G_1, G_2$ as &lt;code>isomorphic&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a graph $G_0$ and $G_1$, if it is so that vertex and edge of $G_0$ is a subset of vertex and edge of $G_1$ then $G_0$ is called a &lt;code>subgraph&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Two points are &lt;code>adjacent&lt;/code> if there is a edge joining them. A vertex is &lt;code>incident&lt;/code> to edge if the vertex is the end of the edge. A vertex which has a edge joining itself to itself is called a &lt;code>loop&lt;/code>. Two edges with same pair of vertex are called &lt;code>parallel&lt;/code>. A graph is &lt;code>simple&lt;/code> if it has no loops or parallel edges. A &lt;code>complete&lt;/code> graph is a graph in which &lt;em>every&lt;/em> two point are adjacent i.e they have a edge between them. A complete graph with $n$ vertices is denoted with $K_n$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If $n$ is the number of vertices of a graph, the total number of possible edges (or, number of edges in a complete graph) are $\binom{n}{2} = \frac{1}{2} n(n-1).$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A graph is &lt;code>finite&lt;/code> if cardinality of vertices and edges are finite. If a graph has infinitely many vertices OR edges, then it is &lt;code>infinite&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$\star$ Generally, unless stated otherwise - we use &lt;em>finite&lt;/em> simple graphs all throughout these notes.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="tactics">Tactics&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>A wide variety of questions can be tackled merely by the above definitions. The tactics to solve such problems are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Reformulate the question&lt;/code> : This sounds simple enough but not always clicks to mind by a first look. After translating the question in graph theoritic terms and &lt;strong>constructing a graph&lt;/strong>, a few too many questions are tremendously simplified to some form of logical argument or something to do with the data provided/inferred.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Parity&lt;/code> : Somehow reach contradictions with even-odd arguments. Works best if the question already provides some concrete data on some variable being even/odd.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Coloring&lt;/code> : Usually works great when some form of trait is to be demonstrated among $2 + k$ objects. Then the problem can be reduced to showing monochromatic structure among these $2+k$ objects.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Pigeonhole principle&lt;/code> : If we put $n$ pigeons in less than $n$ pigeonholes, then at least one pigeonhole contains more than one pigeons. Simple enough to state, but it might take a while to frame the question to use this, the most apt use case is when paired with the above mention &amp;ldquo;coloring&amp;rdquo; strategy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Neighborhood Dragging&lt;/code> : We consider the neighbourhood (denoted by the set $N$) of two defined objects, or vertex (in the question) and then argue if a foreign object can be in it or not (usually depends on the question for partculars).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>WLOG vertex&lt;/code> : In some instances where the graph isn&amp;rsquo;t particularly defined well, we might WLOG assume a pair of vertex or an edge to exist.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="questions">Questions&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;code>1.&lt;/code> There are 50001 people in a party. Suppose that each of them shakes hands with at least one person. Prove that there must be someone who shakes hands with at least two persons.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>2.&lt;/code> There are $n$ athelete who attend a meeting. For any four athelete, there is one person who has shaked hands with the other three.
Prove that for any four athelete, there must be one person who
shakes hands with the rest of the $n - 1$ athelete.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>3.&lt;/code> [USAMO 1978] Nine mathematicians meet at an international mathematics conference. For any three persons, at least two of them can have a talk in the same language. If each mathematician can speak at most three languages, prove that at least three mathematicians can have a talk in the same language.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>4.&lt;/code> There are $n$ fruit boxes. Any two fruit box have the
same kind of fruit inside and every kind of fruit is contained
in just two fruit boxes. How many kinds of fruit are there?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>5.&lt;/code> In a bus with any $m$ travellers, $m \geqslant 3$, they have only one common friend. If $A$ is friends with $B$ then $B$ is friends with $A$, anyone is not a friend of ownself. How many people are there in the carriage ?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$\dots$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the next post we look at Degree of a Vertex and other related topics.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>